Miguel Jiménez

Curriculum Vitae

Computer Science Department University of Victoria Victoria, British Columbia, Canada miguel@uvic.ca miguel@migueljimenez.co https://migueljimenez.co

Research Interests

My area of research is Software Engineering with a focus on the design and development of architectures and infrastructures for self-adaptive software systems.

My research interests include self-adaptive systems, continuous software engineering, models at run-time and domain specific languages. I am currently working towards automated software evolution of cloud software applications through quality-driven continuous experimentation.

Education

2016-Present Ph.D. in Computer Science - University of Victoria, Victoria, Canada

GPA 3.85/4

Advised by Hausi Müller and Gabriel Tamura

Thesis topic: Continuous software evolution at run-time

2014-2016 M.Sc. in Software Engineering - Universidad Icesi, Cali, Colombia

GPA 3.87/4

Advised by Gabriel Tamura

Thesis: A framework for generating and deploying dynamic performance monitors for self-

adaptive software systems

2009-2014 B.E. in Systems Engineering - Universidad Icesi, Cali, Colombia

GPA 3.21/4 • Engineering Dean's list in semesters VI, VII, VIII and IX

Advised by Angela Villota-Gomez and Gabriel Tamura

Degree project: PaSCAni: A language for run-time V&V of functional requirements (Spanish)

Selected Awards and Honors

2018, 2019	Travel Scholarship, CRA-URMD Grad Cohort
2017, 2018	UVic Graduate Award, University of Victoria
2017	Howard E. Petch Research Scholarship, University of Victoria
2017, 2018	IBM Advanced Studies Grant, IBM
2016	Doctoral Fellowship (full academic scholarship), University of Victoria
2014	Master's Fellowship (full academic scholarship), Universidad Icesi
2014	Student Loan Forgiveness , Colombian Institute of Educational Credit and Technical Studies
2013	Top ECAES Exam, Colombian Institute for the Promotion of Higher Education
2009	Undergraduate Scholarship (25%), Universidad Icesi
2011-2014	Engineering Dean's list in semesters VI, VII, VIII, & IX, Universidad Icesi

Publications

Refereed Journal Articles

[J.1] Hugo Arboleda, Andrés Paz, Miguel Jiménez, and Gabriel Tamura. "Development and Instrumentation of a Framework for the Generation and Management of Self-Adaptive Enterprise Applications". en. In: *Ingeniería y Universidad* 20 (Dec. 2016), pp. 303–333.

Refereed Conference Proceedings

- [C.1] **Miguel Jiménez**, Luis F. Rivera, Norha M. Villegas, Gabriel Tamura, Hausi A. Müller, and Nelly Bencomo. "Software Engineering at Run-time". In: (Unpublished) To be submitted to ASE 2019.
- [C.2] Luis F. Rivera, Norha M. Villegas, Gabriel Tamura, **Miguel Jiménez**, and Hausi A. Müller. "UML-driven Automated Software Deployment". In: *Proceedings of the 28th Annual International Conference on Computer Science and Software Engineering (CASCON)*. IBM, 2018, pp. 257–268.
- [C.3] Prashanti Angara, Miguel Jiménez, Kirti Agarwal, Harshit Jain, Roshni Jain, Ulrike Stege, Sudhakar Ganti, Hausi A. Müller, and Joanna W. Ng. "Foodie Fooderson a Conversational Agent for the Smart Kitchen". In: Proceedings of the 27th Annual International Conference on Computer Science and Software Engineering (CASCON). IBM, 2017, pp. 247–253.
- [C.4] **Miguel Jiménez**, Norha M. Villegas, Gabriel Tamura, and Hausi A. Müller. "Deployment Specification Challenges in the Context of Large Scale Systems". In: *Proceedings of the 27th Annual International Conference on Computer Science and Software Engineering (CASCON)*. IBM, 2017, pp. 220–226.
- [C.5] Hugo Arboleda, Andrés Paz, **Miguel Jiménez**, and Gabriel Tamura. "A framework for the generation and management of self-adaptive enterprise applications". In: *2015 10th Computing Colombian Conference* (10CCC). 2015, pp. 55–62.

Refereed Workshop Proceedings

- [W.1] Jean-Michel Bruel and **Miguel Jiménez**. "DevOps'18 Education Panel". In: *Software Engineering Aspects of Continuous Development and New Paradigms of Software Production and Deployment*. Ed. by Jean-Michel Bruel, Manuel Mazzara, and Bertrand Meyer. Springer, 2019, pp. 221–226.
- [W.2] **Miguel Jiménez**, Lorena Castaneda, Norha M. Villegas, Gabriel Tamura, Hausi A. Müller, and Joe Wigglesworth. "DevOps Round-Trip Engineering: Traceability from Dev to Ops and Back Again". In: *Software Engineering Aspects of Continuous Development and New Paradigms of Software Production and Deployment*. Ed. by Jean-Michel Bruel, Manuel Mazzara, and Bertrand Meyer. Springer, 2019, pp. 73–88.
- [W.3] **Miguel Jiménez**, Luis F. Rivera, Norha M. Villegas, Gabriel Tamura, Hausi A. Müller, and Nelly Bencomo. "An Architectural Framework for Quality-driven Adaptive Continuous Experimentation". In: *Proceedings of the IEEE/ACM Joint 4th International Workshop on Rapid Continuous Software Engineering and 1st International Workshop on Data-Driven Decisions, Experimentation and Evolution (RCoSE/DDrEE).* In press. 2019.
- [W.4] Miguel Jiménez, Luis F. Rivera, Norha M. Villegas, Gabriel Tamura, Hausi A. Müller, and Pilar Gallego. "DevOps' Shift-Left in Practice: An Industrial Case of Application". In: Software Engineering Aspects of Continuous Development and New Paradigms of Software Production and Deployment. Ed. by Jean-Michel Bruel, Manuel Mazzara, and Bertrand Meyer. Springer, 2019, pp. 205–220.
- [W.5] Miguel A. Jiménez, Ángela V. Gómez, Norha M. Villegas, Gabriel Tamura, and Laurence Duchien. "A Framework for Automated and Composable Testing of Component-Based Services". In: 2014 IEEE 8th International Symposium on the Maintenance and Evolution of Service-Oriented and Cloud-Based Systems (MESOCA). 2014, pp. 1–10.

Selected Posters and Contributed Talks

- [P.1] Miguel Jiménez, Gabriel Tamura, and Hausi Müller. Towards Software Engineering at Run-time Through Continuous Experimentation and Evolution. Poster at 2019 CRA Grad Cohort Workshop for Underrepresented Minorities + Persons with Disabilities (CRA URMD), Waikoloa Village, Hawaii, United States. Mar. 2019.
- [P.] **Miguel Jiménez**, Gabriel Tamura, and Hausi Müller. *Continuous Deployment Specification for Large-Scale Systems*. Poster at the 28th Annual International Conference on Computer Science and Software Engineering (CASCON), Markham, ON, Canada. Oct. 2018.
- [P.2] Miguel Jiménez, Norha M. Villegas, Gabriel Tamura, and Hausi Müller. Round-trip Soft-ware Engineering in DevOps: Making the Infrastructure a Code Committer. Poster at 2018 CRA Grad Cohort Workshop for Underrepresented Minorities + Persons with Disabilities (CRA URMD), San Diego, California, United States. Mar. 2018.
- [P.] **Miguel Jiménez**, Norha M. Villegas, Gabriel Tamura, Hausi Müller, Joe Wigglesworth, and Ian Watts. *DevOps Round-trip Software Engineering: On Traceability from Dev to Ops and back*. Talk at the Consortium for Software Engineering Research (CSER), Markham, ON, Canada. May 2018.
- [P.3] Miguel Jiménez, Prashanti Angara, Harshit Jain, Kirti Agarwal, Roshni Jain, Hausi Müller, Ulrike Stege, and Joanna Ng. Cognitive IoT Recipe Maven: Digital Expertise in the Kitchen. Poster at Centre for Advanced Studies Technical Link Event (CASTLE), Markham, ON, Canada. May 2017.
- [P.4] **Miguel Jiménez**, Hausi Müller, and Gabriel Tamura. *A DSL Approach For Dynamic Performance Monitoring and Deployment*. Petcha Kutcha presentation at the Consortium for Software Engineering Research (CSER), Markham, ON, Canada. Oct. 2016.
- [P.5] Miguel Jiménez, Hausi Müller, and Gabriel Tamura. A DSL Approach For Generating and Deploying Dynamic Performance Monitors for Self-Adaptive Software Systems. Poster at the 26th Annual International Conference on Computer Science and Software Engineering (CASCON), Markham, ON, Canada. Oct. 2016.

Research Experience

Jan 2018 - **Project Lead Student**

Present IBM Advanced Studies + Rigi Research Group, University of Victoria, Canada Advised by Joe Wigglesworth (IBM), Hausi Müller and Gabriel Tamura

Conduct research and collaborate with the team behind IBM Cloud Automation Manager to develop round-trip engineering mechanisms for infrastructure as code, and automate continuous experimentation for deployments on the cloud.

Jan 2014 - Graduate Research Assistant

Aug 2016 i2T/DRISO Research Group, Universidad Icesi, Colombia *Advised by Gabriel Tamura*

- Identified challenges in dynamic performance monitoring of self-adaptive systems and proposed technical solutions following the SOA philosophy to advance the state of the art
- Designed and implemented two domain-specific languages for dynamic monitoring and distributed deployment
- Managed the computing resources of the i2T/DRISO research group's computing grid (15 physical machines)

Jun 2013 - Research Assistant Intern

Dec 2013 i2T/DRISO Research Group, Universidad Icesi, Colombia Advised by Gabriel Tamura

Implemented and conducted quantitative experiments for the matrix multiplication problem.

Teaching and Mentoring Experience

Spring 2018 Graduate Teaching Assistant

Assistance Centre in Computer Science, University of Victoria

Tutored students and assisted them with programming assignments in one-on-one sessions.

2016-2018 Graduate Teaching Assistant

Fundamentals of Programming with Engineering Applications (CSC 111), University of Victoria Instructor: Hausi Müller

- Lectured weekly labs and assisted students with programming and lab assignments
- Co-led weekly meetings and developed teaching material and quizzes
- Developed GradeBuddy, a program to assist teaching assistants and professors in automating the marking of programming assignments
- Developed a multi-platform installation assistant to ease the installation of CLion and its dependencies on Windows, Mac and Linux
- Developed examgen, a program to generate examinations along with their solutions from a YAML input file. The resulting files are rendered to either MEX or Moodle. By creating examgen, we stopped printing 2800 quizzes and reduced marking time by 30h per term
- Deployed an online platform to host and mark programming assignments

Fall 2016 Graduate Teaching Assistant

Data Structures I (CSC 225), University of Victoria

Instructor: Ulrike Stege

Lectured weekly labs, developed scripts to automate marking and graded assignments.

Spring 2016 Technical Advisor

Undergraduate degree project, Interactive Media Design Program - Universidad Icesi

Knowledge management and dissemination: alternative soccer culture

Student: Juan David Flórez Bautista

Spring 2015 Tutor

Undergraduate degree project, Interactive Media Design Program - Universidad Icesi

Folii: natural and interactive encyclopedia mediated by citizen science

Students: Juan Pablo Pérez, Mauricio Alberto Toro

Spring 2011 *Teaching Assistant*

Data Structures and Algorithms, Universidad Icesi

Instructor: Angela Villota-Gomez

Graded programming assignments.

Invited Talks

- [T.1] **Miguel Jiménez**. *Continuous Value Delivery with DevOps (Spanish)*. Online webinar for university alumni, Universidad Icesi. Mar. 2019.
- [T.2] **Miguel Jiménez**, Gabriel Tamura, and Hausi Müller. *Towards Continuous Assurance of Non-Functional Requirements Through Continuous Experimentation*. Presentation at the 2nd Workshop on DevOps, Annual International Conference on Computer Science and Software Engineering (CASCON). Markham, Canada. Nov. 2018.

Service and Volunteering

2011-2012 Volunteer instructor for the Web Programming Club

Universidad Icesi, Cali, Colombia

Developed teaching material and lectured members of the programming club on HTML, CSS and JavaScript.

Skills

Programming Languages

Java, Xtend JavaScript, CSS, HTML

Python Go C# Oz

ShellScript

■ Technical Skills

Architecture Design
Build Automation
Containerized Applications
Continuous Delivery
Data mining (basic)
Infrastructure Provision
Language Engineering
Microservices Architecture
Object Oriented Programming
Performance Monitoring
Service Component Architecture

Languages

Spanish (Native) English (Fluent) French (Elementary)